<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in Oxford-shire; by Nicholas Cantrel, Master in Arts. Published at the request of Sir Richard Blunt</title>
            <author>Cantrell, Nicholas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17927</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4588</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118531</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853738</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853738</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19133</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17927)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19133)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1166:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in Oxford-shire; by Nicholas Cantrel, Master in Arts. Published at the request of Sir Richard Blunt</title>
                  <author>Cantrell, Nicholas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. L[ownes] for Matthevv Lownes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19133:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19133:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED IN <hi>OXFORD-SHIRE;</hi> BY NICHOLAS CANTREL, Maſter in Arts.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed at the requeſt of Sir RICHARD BLVNT.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> for MATTHEVV LOWNES. 1624.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19133:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19133:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IOSH. 24.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>But as for me and my houſe, we will ſerve the Lord.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE beſt cognizance that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace hath, is Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and a continuall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in grace; according unto that of <hi>David; Such as be planted in the houſe of God, ſhall flouriſh in the Courts of the houſe of the Lord; they alſo ſhall bring forth more fruit in their age, Pſal.</hi> 92.12. Manie men indeed begin well, but in continuance of time they are wearie of well-doing, and their end is not anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: they begin in the ſpirit, but they end in the fleſh. Oh it paſſeth, in their yonger yeers, how zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous they are for Gods cauſe, how deare his teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies are unto them: but, as if the heat of their devotion depended upon their youth, it abates by degrees, and the older they growe, the colder they are to Godwards. like the fooliſh Virgins in the Goſpel, towards the time that the Bridegrome is comming, they are ſleeping, without oile in their lampes, and ſo doe loſe their reward.</p>
            <p>We find by experience, that that parable which our Saviour tells us of the Sower, is too true; and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19133:3"/>there be temporarie beleevers, who at firſt receive the ſeed of the word with gladneſſe, but the cares of this world, &amp; the deceitfulnes of riches choake the word, and in the harveſt-time of their life they are made unfruitfull. Manie, that (like <hi>David</hi>) have bin as ſtarres in Iſrael, to lead the people into the houſe of God, have growne dimme at laſt, and loſt their glorie. Now, as if with <hi>Saul,</hi> the good Spirit had forſaken them, and the evill Spirit had taken poſſeſsion of them, they are not the ſame they were: they are changed from their firſt love, and by tranſgreſſing the commandements of God, do loſe that hold which they had of grace. Their neglect of good duties, their converſation with the wicked of this world, their repoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon worldly vanities, are ſignes whereby it is to be feared, leſt God doe glorifie himſelfe upon them by his iudgements, ſince they doe leave off to glorifie God by their godly life and example.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is not enough for a man to begin well, but he muſt proceed more and more in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and in grace, and everie day take-out a new leſſon in pietie, and ſet forth unto the world a fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer copie of his life. The unprofitable ſervant was not condemned for not keeping, but for not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing his talent. Even reprobates have gon very farre in grace, and by their fearfull falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, have left us examples to take heed how wee ſtand ſecure of the judgements of God. Hee was never truely good, who had not alwaies a deſire to proove better: for if wee look into the examples of the Saints and ſervants of God, this propertie
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19133:3"/>wee may generallie obſerve in them, and we ſhall find them ever to have bin beſt at the laſt.</p>
            <p>To the end that I may ſhew that to bee true in part, which I have ſpoken in generall, I have brought before your eyes the example of zealous <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> that renowned ſervant of God; in whoſe mouth the praiſes of his God (like a Swan-like ſong) are now ſweeteſt towards his latter end. The flouriſhing yeares of his life he had ſpent in the ſervice of <hi>Moſes,</hi> behaving himſelfe valiantly, in fighting againſt the enemies of the Lord: and now that <hi>Moſes</hi> was dead, he was choſen by God to ſucceed in the ſame place and charge, namely, to be the Leader of the Iſraelites.</p>
            <p>It is well worth your noting, to behold how faithfully and carefully this good ſervant of God behaved himſelfe in ſo weightie an office: For when the Lord by his hand had brought his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple into the land which he ſware unto their fathers that hee would give them, and had given reſt unto Iſrael from all their enemies round about, ſo that now they had a ſettled policie &amp; government both in Church and Common-wealth; <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> did not thus thinke with himſelfe: <q>I have done enough for my time, from henceforth I will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burthen my ſelfe of all cares and troubles; the reſt of my life I will ſpend with as much delight as I can, and betake my ſelfe wholly unto my eaſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Such imaginations as theſe, were farre from <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuah;</hi> hee knew ſo high a Calling as his, did require othergeſſe reſolutions: and therefore
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19133:4"/>his thoughts were wholly taken up in well-man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging the affaires of the Common-wealth, in providing that the Commandements of his God might be put in execution; that true Religion might everie where be eſtabliſhed, idolatrie bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and that God might be glorified all in all; as you may perceive by the 22.23. and 24. chapters of this booke.</p>
            <p>As for his own private houſe &amp; familie, the well ordering &amp; guiding of it muſt needs challenge the higheſt praiſe and admiration of godlie and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous minds. No looſeneſſe was ſuffered to raigne here, no impietie to infect here, no buſie Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants were ſufferd to neſt themſelves here, being the onelie inſtruments which the unhappie world, in theſe laſt and dangerous times, cheriſheth to its owne confuſion. None muſt live with <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> but ſuch as would live after <hi>Ioſhuahs</hi> patterne and preſcription: None muſt ſerve <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> but ſuch as would ſerve <hi>Ioſhuahs</hi> God, in uprightneſſe and ſinceritie. Such was his godlie reſolution, ſuch his care, ſuch his zeale. Nor was this affection in him by fitts, bred of a ſudden and vaniſhing hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; but it was firme and fixed in his heart, even to the laſt minute of his life: yea, and did then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in its greateſt excellencie unto the world, when as he himſelfe was ready to leave the world.</p>
            <p>For now his dying day drawing neere apace, this good ſervant of God (as if his ſoule had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther care to poſſeſſe it, but the wellfare of the Church, and the continuance of true Religion) for this end and purpoſe aſſembles the Iſraelites
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19133:4"/>to Sichem, their Elders, their Heads, their Iudges and Officers; who accordingly preſented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves before God. Here <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> begins with a Commemoration of the benefits which God had done for the people, and puts them in mind of the manifold deliverances which hee wrought for them; namely, by delivering them from the furie of ſo manie fierce &amp; dreadfull nations that fought againſt them, and by caſting them out before them: then, by giving them a land wherein they did not labour, and cities which they built not, and vineyards and olive-trees which they planted not. For ſuch and ſo great benefits of Almightie God, hee onelie requires, that they for their parts would expreſſe their thankfulneſſe by ſerving the Lord in ſinceritie and uprightneſſe, and by having nothing to doe with thoſe falſe gods which their fathers ſerved beyond the floud, and in Aegypt.</p>
            <p>Oh how inflamed is that zeale! how indefati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable is that diligence, which neither the coldneſſe of age can extinguiſh, nor the feebleneſſe of decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nature can diminiſh! <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> like a good Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, being to leave the houſe of his Lord, the Church of his God, would leave (as much as lies in him) all in good order before he goes; would ſee that true religion ſhould be thorowly planted. Like a good Paſtor, before he leaves his flock, faine would hee gather together the outcaſts of Iſrael, and bring all into one fold: He would faine make all that dwelt in Iſrael, to be true Iſraelites indeed.</p>
            <p>Here (my beloved) you have a faire mirrour of pietie; but wherein you may behold the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19133:5"/>diſproportion of theſe times: For where is that Authoritie which ſo beſtirres it ſelfe in Gods cauſe? where is hee that will undertake that in his private houſe, which <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> doth in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth? O barren world, which doſt gather ſtrength in ſinne, by running towards thy end! needs muſt thy ſinnes be purged with a deluge of fire, ſince the beſt amongſt us are but briars and thornes, and have not ſo much as one dram of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuahs</hi> zeale.</p>
            <p>Well, but to proceed: <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> (you ſee) leaves no meanes unaſſaied to bring this good purpoſe of his to a wiſhed effect. But if this unrulie multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude would not obey the commandements of God, of that God which had wrought ſuch great things for them, nor keepe his Covenant: If the hardneſſe of their hearts were ſuch, that they could be content to enjoy his benefits, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme no ſervice: hee ſets before them life and death, this day, to chooſe which they will; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would ſerve the gods which their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſerved, that were beyond the floud; or the gods of the Amorites, in whoſe land they dwelt. As for himſelfe, he is firmely bent and reſolute, both for himſelfe and his familie, to maintaine Gods cauſe againſt the whole world; <hi>But as for mee,</hi> &amp;c. Now from this practice of <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> wee learne what is our dutie; namely, this teacheth us, that if all the world would go from God, <hi>Yet eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of us particularly is bound to cleave unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This doctrine which <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> had well laide up in memorie, now to make uſe of it, and by his rare
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19133:5"/>example to commend it unto poſteritie, hee had learned in <hi>Moſes</hi> ſchoole: <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a multitude</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>to doe evill,</hi> Exod. 23.2. which as it prooves, that wee muſt not ſuffer our ſelves to bee carried away into anie evill courſe whatſoever, by doing that which the greater part doth; ſo eſpecially in the things that concerne the honour and worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>And this ſtands by good reaſon: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> for if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider our calling, firſt, wee are choſen out of the world, to be a peculiar people unto God; and therefore what others doe, wee ought not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard: wee are the children, wee are the ſervants of God; wherfore as the eyes of ſervants looke unto the hand of their Maſters, even ſo muſt our eyes wait upon the Lord our God, Pſal. 123.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the next place, if wee conſider the truth of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; God is conſtant in his purpoſe, nothing can make him change, nothing can make him breake his covenant with us. Hee is able, and will profect us againſt all adverſaries, if wee relie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his power, and put our truſt in him. If we faile not in his ſervice, he will not faile in his promiſes: A crowne of glorie is the high price of our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; nothing can take it from us, if wee continue to the end. And ſhall wee then bereave our ſelves of ſo great a reward, as makes us happy and bleſſed for ever, by going backe from the ſervice of ſo good, ſo powerfull, ſo juſt a God, either for feare or for favour of vaine man?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> A third and laſt reaſon why wee ſhould cleave unto GOD, though the whole World ſhould
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19133:6"/>goe from God, is, becauſe though wee have never ſo manie preſidents in this kind, yet no multitude can warrant us againſt the juſtice &amp; judgements of God. If wee ſinne with the multitude, wee ſhall be puniſhed with the multitude. For when wee are called to give up our account, it will not bee ſufficient for us to ſay, wee have done as wee ſaw others doe: but as we are partakers of their ſinnes, ſo wee muſt partake of their ſufferings too. Mark (my brtheren) and take <hi>Aaron</hi> for example, who becauſe he ranne the ſame courſe with the people, and being overcome with the importunitie of the unrulie multitude, conſented to their idolatrie, in making them a golden calfe, and worſhipping it; was not ſuffered to come into the land of promiſe, Numb. 20.24.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, if wee look unto the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the holy men, whoſe praiſes are regiſtred by the ſpirit of God, we ſhal find it recorded to their high commendation, that their hearts were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſtrait and right in the ſervice of God: they cleaved ſtedfaſtly unto the true worſhip of God, though living in the midſt of a froward and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe generation. When all the world was ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wickedneſſe, yet even then was juſt <hi>Noah</hi> a Preacher of righteouſneſſe, 2. <hi>Pet. chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Abraham</hi> built an Altar unto the Lord, and called upon the name of the Lord, when he dwelt amongſt the fierce and idolatrous Heathens, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. Righteous <hi>Lot</hi> was not without the feare of God, nor did depart from the commandements of God, though living amongſt the beaſtly Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19133:6"/>his righteous ſoule was vexed with the uncleane converſation of thoſe wicked men, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. Laſtly, in a word, <hi>Daniel</hi> did not ſhrink to pray openly unto his God, notwithſtanding that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked decree of the king were publiſhed to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie; whereby he was brought in danger of his life, for the zeale and freedome of his devotion, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Alas, Alas (my brethren)! needes muſt the examples of theſe zealous Saints riſe up in judgement againſt us, and condemne the coldneſſe and hypocriſie of our wretched times: in which the moſt part of men are readie to ſtartle aſide from the profeſſion of that faith and religion, in which manie yeares they have bin taught, even upon the leaſt earthly advantage that ſhall be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto them. If there be hope that they may better their decaied fortunes: if they may pleaſe men, give content, and currie fauour; they will eaſily be brought to fall from Chriſt, to renounce his Goſpel. Thus the foundations of the earth are out of courſe, and none like <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> to beare up the pillars of it.</p>
            <p>Let but the ſound of a change in Religion ſtrike the eares of men; what a number of falſe and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering hearts will ſoone be diſcloſed, who will runne with the multitude, and expoſe that truth whereby they ſhould bee ſaved, unto an open ſhame! And why is this? but becauſe men doe not value the great and pretious promiſes of Chriſt, as they ſhould; they doe not love Chriſt for himſelfe; they care not for Religion,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19133:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>further than it may ſtand with their worldly and carnall ends. Yet here is a ground of comfort for all them that doe faithfully ſerve the Lord, and ſtedfaſtly cleave unto him; for he will cleave ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly unto them: he will not forſake them, nor leave them in the hand of their enemies, but will be readie to aſſiſt them, and to comfort them at all aſſaies. Yea, let them not be diſcouraged nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maied with the manifold offences which they finde in this world: God will ſhorten theſe wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched times for his Elects ſake; when it ſhall be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everie man according to his faith. Onely in the meane time, let them poſſeſſe their ſoules in pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and reſolve with <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> to be conſtant in the ſervice of God, how-ever the world varies; for if they continue to the end, undoubtedly they ſhall obtaine that promiſed crowne of glorie.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the connexion of my text; the words themſelves doe now crave your attention: in which, being (as they are) a Proteſtation, you have theſe two circumſtances; Firſt, the partie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting; whoſe qualitie and condition you are to conſider: Secondly, the extent of his Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Hee that proteſteth here, is <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Iſraelites, famous amongſt them for his Conqueſts in the warres, and no leſſe renowned for his Counſailes in the times of peace; in a word, the chief man among them, both in power, dignitie and authortie: from which ariſeth this point of inſtruction; <hi>God requires of the greateſt men, the greateſt zeale for his glorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19133:7"/>
            <p> A point which you may ſee notably proved, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.7. where <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, being ſent to reproove <hi>David</hi> for thoſe heinous ſinnes of murther and adulterie which hee had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, enforceth the arguments of his reproofe from the promotion and dignitie which God had rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>David</hi> unto, and from the benefits which were conferred upon him: <hi>Thou art the man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> having made <hi>David</hi> to pronounce the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death upon himſelfe, by a parable which he told him): <hi>thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed thee king over Iſrael, and delivered thee out of the hand of Saul, and gave thee thy Lords houſe, and thy Lords wives into thy boſome, and gave thee the houſe of Iſrael and of Iudah; and would more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, if that had bin too little, have given thee ſuch and ſuch things: wherefore haſt thou deſpiſed the commandement of the Lord, to do evill in his ſight?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed there is good reaſon why the Lord ſhould require the ſincereſt and greateſt ſervice of them, whom he hath exalted unto the higheſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and upon whom he hath beſtowed his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits more abundantly than upon others. For firſt of all, by a like reaſon; Doth not the husbandman expect the goodlieſt croppe from that ground up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which hee hath beſtowed the greateſt coſt and labour? Doe not parents alſo expect the greateſt duetie and affection from that childe, towards whom they have bin moſt indulgent and carefull in his education? So likewiſe it is with the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter towards his ſervant: If his bountie have bin extraordinary towards him, hee may juſtly looke
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19133:8"/>for extraordinarie reſpect and ſervice at his hands. And ſhall not Almightie God require of them the ſincereſt ſervice, and greateſt zeale for his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, whom hee hath raiſed unto the greateſt digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie?</p>
            <p>Againe, ſecondly, if wee looke about in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie courſe of nature, that will teach us another ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient reaſon of this point. The higheſt Spheares, are not they the ſwifteſt in motion? and doe they not carrie about with them the inferiour orbes, by their celeritie? The biggeſt ſtarres in the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are they not evermore the brighteſt? and doe they not give luſtre unto the leſſer ſtarres? Now tell mee; If God doe preſcribe ſuch order to his dumbe creatures, how much more will hee require, that the ſame order ſhould be kept in his reaſonable creature, in his more noble creature (man)? Thus then wee may conclude by a like reaſon: Men that beare authoritie, that are emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in power and dignitie, that excell in riches and Command, are placed in the higheſt Spheares of humane ſocietie; to this end, that (like ſonnes of God) they might ſhine brightly unto their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours by their godly life and example.</p>
            <p>Such arguments as theſe, it were fit that they ſhould alwaies beare in their minds, leſt, being great in this world, they forget the hand that rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them; &amp; that befall them which <hi>David</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of: <hi>Man being in honour</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath no underſtanding, but is compared unto the beaſts that periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the divell is well ſeene in ſubtile ſophiſtrie:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19133:8"/>hee uſeth to frame a prepoſterous argument, and to inferre <hi>(à poſitione beneficij, depoſitionem of ficij)</hi> from the poſition of dignitie, the depoſition of duetie. <q>Let poore men (ſaith hee) and ſuch as be of a lowly and humble ſpirit tremble at the word of God. Let them be dejected, and groane at the ſight of their ſinnes, who want the good things of this world to comfort them. Great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions become them that bee in great places. Wilt thou goe with the multitude, and bring them forth into the houſe of God? This is the way to make thee leſſe than thou art. Doe not trouble thy ſelfe with frequenting religious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, nor with mortifying contemplations, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> enter thorow, even to the dividing aſunder of the ſoule and the Spirit. Learne to have the advantage of thy great fortune; one houre in a Sabbath is enough to ſpend in devotion, the reſt thou maiſt beſtow upon thy ſelfe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus doth Satan goe about to delude man, and make the bleſſings of God become ſnares in his way; perſwading him, that by how much he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove others, he hath by ſo much, more liberty than others. Where, on the contrarie, God is no accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of perſons, nor regards heeanie man the more for that which he hath: but in as much as he hath received all from him, hee lookes for the greater feare and obedience at his hands. The more ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents a man hath received, the greater account hath hee to make for them.</p>
            <p>The uſe therefore of this point ſerves for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction unto all them whom God hath advanced
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19133:9"/>in this world, upon whom he hath beſtowed his outward favours and bleſſings; to teach them to be alwaies mindfull what, and of whom they have received them, and to be carefull to walke wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of their high calling. Theſe outward gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which make men to be eſteemed and admired in the world (riches, honours, power, and pree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence) they are not borne with men, men are not borne unto them; they have them not by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: But they are the gifts of God, he beſtowes them where he pleaſeth; and where he beſtowes them, there he expects, that (like good ſtewards) men ſhould faithfully diſpoſe of them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.21.</note> to his glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>hath appointed a day, in the which he will iudge the world with righteouſneſſe:</hi> then ſhall all men riſe to give an account of their doings. Not the pooreſt man that lives, but hath manie waies taſted of the benefits and bountie of God, and therefore ſtands accountable for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice &amp; for his thankefulneſſe. He that hath bin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull in a little, ſhall be beaten with the fewer ſtripes; but <hi>the mightie</hi> (ſaith the wiſe man) <hi>ſhall he mightily tormented, Wiſ.</hi> 6.6.</p>
            <p>For why? Great and publicke examples have this condition annexed unto them; that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſinne onely to themſelves, but muſt needs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound oftentimes even unto a whole countrie. If the maſter of a houſe bee given to ſwearing, the whole familie will abuſe his example, and take the ſame libertie in that horrible ſinne. If he care not to breake the Sabbath by unſeaſonable ſports, they that live with him, will have as little care to keep it holy.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:19133:9"/>
            <p> O let not ſuch a ſiniſter perſwaſion as this is, blind their eyes; that becauſe the world flatters them, therefore God will be the more favourable to them; or becauſe they find God to be more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to them in the things of this world, that therefore the caſe will bee ſo with them too in the world to come. No (ſaith Chriſt, ſpeaking of them that did put more confidence in their riches, than in God), <hi>A rich man ſhall hardly enter into the kingdom of heaven:</hi> Nay, he goes further than ſo, &amp; tells us, that <hi>it is eaſier for a Camell to goe thorow the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the kingdome of God, Math.</hi> 19.23.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Lazarus</hi> (as it is in the parable) died, hee was ſtraightwaies carried by the Angels into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> boſome; but <hi>Dives</hi> when he died was in torments. But what was it that <hi>Dives</hi> had done? wee doe not read of anie horrible crime that was laide unto his charge: Onely (this was all) he ſerved the fleſh &amp; the world, in ſtead of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God; and did not return that which hee had received from God, to the glorie of God. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon was that anſwer given him: <hi>Sonne, remember that thou in thy life time receivedſt thy pleaſures, Luke</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>Thus, though a man may be accounted happie in this world; though he may appear an honeſt man to the world-ward; yet is not this enough to ſave him: he may be in danger of going unto hell, if he can give no better account of his ſervice unto God.</p>
            <p>Oh how will they doe then, upon whom God beſtowes temporall bleſſings with a plentifull
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19133:10"/>hand; unto whom he gives all manner of meanes, and occaſions of doing good in this life; whom hee compaſſeth about with the light of his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel: if after ſuch ſweet benefits they be not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and zealous to promote his glory? What can I ſay more than this, that life and death is ſet before us, and with bended knees beſeech the God of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, even the Father of our Lord Ieſus, to make us carefull to chooſe the better part, to make us wiſe to our ſalvation?</p>
            <p>Now from the qualitie of the partie proteſting, in the next place I come to the extent of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation: <hi>[As for mee and my houſe, wee will ſerve the Lord:] Ioſhuah</hi> thinkes it not enough that hee himſelfe be religious, that he in his owne perſon be the ſervant of the Lord; unleſſe thoſe that hee keeps about him, be thus piouſly affected; unleſſe they be religious too. Hee will binde all that live with him, in the ſame bond of duetie unto God. None ſhall ſerve <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> that will not ſerve that God which <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> ſerves. <hi>I will ſerve the Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ioſhuah</hi>); yet not only ſo, but <hi>I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord.</hi> Hence I commend unto your conſiderations this memorable doctrine: <hi>The true ſervants of God will keep none in their houſes, but ſuch as ioine with them in the true worſhipping of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This point, if you reade the 101. Pſalme, you may ſee proved to the full: where <hi>David,</hi> ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down what government he wil obſerve in his houſe and kingdome, ſhewes what manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons they are that hee will refuſe, and who they be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19133:10"/>whom he will chuſe to live in his houſe with him. <hi>Mine eyes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>look unto ſuch as are faithfull in the land, that they may dwell with mee. Whoſo lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a godly life, hee ſhall be my ſervant. There ſhall no deceitfull perſon dwell in my houſe: he that telleth lies, ſhall not tarrie in my ſight. I ſhall ſoone deſtroy all the ungodly that are in the land; that I may root out all wicked doers from the City of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Now the reaſon of this point, is firſt drawne from the conformitie which there is betwixt the Catholike Church and everie true member there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: No uncleane thing comes within the bounds and pale of the Catholike Church; nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bides in that, which is not pure and holy. And therefore he that is a member of this Church, will ſuffer none to bee neare about him (as much as lies in him) who is not a member of the ſame body, who is not a free denizon of the Citie of his God. As in naturall homogeneall bodies, everie part doth <hi>(ſuſcipere rationem totius)</hi> participate of the name and nature of the whole; ſhunnes what is contrarie to that nature; and moſt willingly ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers it ſelfe to that which is of the ſame kinde: For example; The leaſt droppe of water hath the name of its Element; hath the entire properties of it; partakes of the round figure of that Element; and beſt agrees and unites it ſelfe to water. In like manner it is with the fire and the reſt of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; being homogeneall bodies, they are not compounded of anie parts, which agree not in the name and nature of the whole. So it is with the true members of that myſticall bodie whereof
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19133:11"/>Chriſt is the head; they cannot ſuffer themſelves to be combined with wicked perſons and unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers: no, they will aſſociate none unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by their good wills, who are not endued with grace, and goodneſſe, and a godly converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being the true qualities and markes of that inviſible Chuch, wherof they themſelves are true members.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reaſon is drawne from the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences which muſt needs follow, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> if they ſhould ſuffer wicked and ungodly perſons to dwell in their houſes. For, firſt of all, where ſuch Iſmae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites are, God cannot have his due: needs muſt his honour be blaſphemed; his name cannot be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified; there can be no true peace in that houſe, but <hi>(infida ſocietas)</hi> a treacherous ſocietie.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</note> There will be perpetuall enmitie betwixt the ſeed of the woman, and the ſeed of the ſerpent. If the ſonne of the bonds woman bee ſuffered to tarrie in the houſe with the ſonne of the promiſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.9.</note> he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leave mocking and perſecuting, untill hee bee caſt out.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.22.</note> 
               <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> cannot lie together in the ſame womb, without ſtrugling together, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Rebecca</hi> to paine.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.7.</note> The Arke of God cannot reſt with Dagon. Beſides, if wee admit this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly mixture, another inconvenience muſt needs happen; the ſound members of that bodie wil be in danger, where there is anie rotten mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſuffered to hang on: Hereſie and Vice are as infectious as the plague it ſelfe. When the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle charged the Corinthians to excommunicate, and put out of their aſſemblie the inceſtuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19133:11"/>he urgeth this reaſon; <hi>A little leaven</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>leaveneth the whole lumpe; purge out therefore the old leaven, that yee may be a new lumpe, as yee are unleavened,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point; they can never truly and ſincerely ſerve God, who doe not cauſe them that live in their houſes, to ſerve him in like manner.</p>
            <p>The uſe of this ſerves in the firſt place for infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, to ſhew us what manner of proficients we are in the ſchoole of grace; how ſtedfaſtly we cleave unto the covenant of God; how perfectly we walke in his waies; how neere wee have attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to that heavenly communion of Saints. For if our converſation be in heaven, all our delight will bee upon the Saints on earth. <hi>Wee know</hi> (ſaith S.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn) that we have paſſed from death unto life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee love the bretheren.</hi> Wee know by this, that wee love God, and that wee are beloved of God, if we love his ſervants, and make much of them that feare the Lord.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.3.</note> And then (with <hi>David)</hi> wee walk in our houſes with a perfect heart, when with one ſpirit, &amp; with one ſoule, both our ſelves, and thoſe that be under us, do ſerve the Lord; then wee ſhall be ſure of a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>When the Lord did ſo familiarly converſe with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and create him the father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, it was with this <hi>proviſo;</hi> for (ſaith hee) <hi>I know him, that hee will command his ſonnes, and his houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold after him, that they keepe the way of the Lord, to doe righteouſneſſe and iudgement, Geneſ.</hi> 18. When <hi>David</hi> was choſen of God, and pronounced a man after Gods owne heart, it was with reſpect
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19133:12"/>unto the faithfulneſſe and truth of his, in ruling them that were committed to his charge, prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with all his power, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.72.</p>
            <p>Wouldſt thou find that favour in the eyes of the Lord, that <hi>Abraham</hi> did? then thou muſt follow the ſteppes of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith. Wouldſt thou be as deare unto God, as <hi>David</hi> was? then with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> thou muſt ſeeke to enlarge the glorie of God. Thy eyes muſt look unto ſuch as be faithfull in the land, that they may dwell with thee: hee, and none but hee muſt be thy ſervant, that leadeth a godly life. In a word, wouldſt thou, with <hi>Ioſhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> enter into the promiſed Canaan? then, with <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> thou muſt bee zealous for Gods cauſe. Though all the world ſhould ſtagger, and revolt from God, &amp; forſake his Covenant; yet muſt thou maintain his worſhip: thou muſt obey his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; thou muſt reverence his word, &amp; bear this reſolution; <hi>I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond uſe of this point ſerves to diſcover unto us the backward diſpoſition of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of this age; in whom wee find no ſuch zeale for Gods glory, no ſuch forwardnes in this ſervice. Alas, alas! where have wee one endewed with <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, to teach the commandements and ordinances of God unto his poſteritie? where is one inſpired with this zeale of <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> to proteſt ſincerely, <hi>I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord?</hi> We may runne to and fro with <hi>Ieremie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 5.1.</note> and ſearch long enough, before wee finde the man either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſmall or great.</p>
            <p>Tell mee; Is not the vigour and force of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19133:12"/>ſtrangely abated and decayed, when moſt places in the world (like <hi>Caiaphas</hi> hall) are filled with a rabblement of Vice; Hereticks, Atheiſts, Epicures (pell-mell) all of all ſorts, ſaving of good men? We are falne upon thoſe laſt and deſperate times of the world, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> foretold ſhould come, and hath lively ſet forth, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. <hi>This know</hi> (ſaith he), <hi>that in the laſt dayes ſhall come pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous times; for men ſhall be lovers of their owne ſelves, covetous, boaſters, proud, blaſphemers, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of thoſe that are good, lovers of pleaſures, more than lovers of God; having a forme of godlineſſe, but denying the power thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Divell hath gotten the ſtart of the world, and hath ſet up in the mindes of men his idols of worldly pompe and vanitie. What is more neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, than the Commandements of God? what is ſlighted ſo much, as his ſervice? and who are ſo backward in it, as they that ſhould be moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward? All the counſell that I can give in this caſe, is that of <hi>David, O conſider this yee that forget God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm</hi> 50.22</note> 
               <hi>leſt he pluck you away, and there be none to deliver you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third and laſt uſe of this point, is for exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to ſtirre up thoſe who have the charge and command of others, unto the carefull and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable performance of this duety, by all meanes to enlarge and advance the kingdome of Chriſt: and where God hath eſtabliſhed them, that there they ſhould eſtabliſh godlineſſe. As this is the greateſt and weightieſt duetie that lyes upon men in this world; ſo hath it the greateſt arguments, and the weightieſt motives to enforce it.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:19133:13"/>
            <p> Firſt, the benefit which the performance of our duety herein, brings with it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the danger that we runne into, by the neglect hereof.</p>
            <p>Godlineſſe is the greateſt gaine to a Chriſtian that is: it hath not onely the promiſes of this life, but of the life to come; for, <hi>in ſerving the Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) there is great reward.</hi> Whereas on the contrarie, an everlaſting curſe of miſerie and contempt, is laid upon thoſe wretches that are neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in his worke.</p>
            <p>When the Lord ſent his Prophet to reprove <hi>Eli,</hi> and to threaten the taking away of the Prieſthood from him and his poſteritie, becauſe his ſonnes ran into a ſlander, and their father ſtayed them not; this is the ſentence that the Lord addes withall: <hi>For, them that honour mee</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>I will honour; and they that deſpiſe me, ſhal be deſpiſed,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30.</p>
            <p>Would you hear what gratious &amp; ſingular pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges the true ſervants of God have? liſten then to that which <hi>David</hi> tells you: <hi>The eyes of the Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) are over the righteous; and his eares are open unto their prayers.</hi> Againe: <hi>The righteous cry, and the Lord heareth them, and delivereth them out of all their troubles.</hi> And once more hee addes this in the ſame Pſalme: <hi>The Lord delivereth the ſoules of his ſervants, and all they that put their truſt in him, ſhall not be deſtitute, Pſal.</hi> 34. Nay moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, whoſoever hee is that is zealous for the Lord, ſhall not only have the Lord for his protector and defender in all his afflictious; but for his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor and Director in all his affaires, as the ſame
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19133:13"/>Prophet doth notablly expreſſe it in another place; <hi>What man is hee</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) that feareth the Lord? him ſhall he teach in the way that he ſhall chooſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe benefits and teſtimonies of Gods father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affection and care towards them, are ordinarie, and dayly extended to them: but what ſolace or delight is there, that this world can afford, to bee compared with the joy and comfort, which the dying ſervant of God feeles, when hee can truely ſay (his conſcience bearing him witneſſe), <q>Lord, I have brought up them in thy knowledge and feare, whom thou gaveſt into my hands: I have not hid thy commandements from my poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: The talents which I received of thee, loe, here they are encreaſed. I made it the ſcope of my life, to ſet forth thy glory, and to enlarge thy kingdome: Let not my Lord bee angrie at the weakneſſe of his unprofitable ſervant. I have fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mee thinkes indeed I heare the Iudge of the world pronouncing that ſweet Elogie, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <q>Wel done good &amp; faithful ſervant; thou haſt bin faithfull in little, I will make thee Ruler over much: Enter in into thy maſters joy,</q> 
               <hi>Mat,</hi> 25.21. And will hee not on the contrarie pronounce that dreadfull ſentence upon thoſe that have abuſed his goods? <hi>Servi mali &amp; cunctatores,</hi> 
               <q>Yee evill and ſlothfull ſervants, where are my Talents? why doe I not receive mine own with advantage? how is it, that yee have buried them in the earth, in the earthly vanities and pleaſures
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19133:14"/>of this world? get ye therefore out of my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, into utter darknes.</q> This is that ſevere ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> our Savior hath forewarn'd us of, being as yet converſant amongſt us in humilitie. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it will be our wiſdome to thinke of it ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that wee may bee out of the danger of it, when he ſhall appeare in his glorie.</p>
            <p>For (alas!) otherwiſe what unſpeakable ſhame, what horrour and confuſion will betide us in that day; when as ſo manie zealous Saints and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord, who have waded thorow the ſtorms of tyrannie and perſecution, and have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned their conſtant profeſſion of the Goſpell of Ieſus, with the innocencie of their godly lives, and have ſealed it with their bloods; when theſe ſo manie ſhall be our judges? O bleſſed Saints whoſe ſoules are in heaven, where you doe follow the lamb whereſoever he goes, clothed in white robes, as the livery of your innocencie, &amp; palms in your hands, as the enſignes of victorie! how will your zeal, and your forwardneſſe to ſet forth the glory of God, condemne the coldnes and backwardnes of your poſteritie!</p>
            <p>Now therefore conſider how fearefull the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of Reprobates is: they muſt never look to ſee the face of God: They that will not ſerve the Lord, the Lord will caſt them forth from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: God will ſpue them forth, whoſoever they they be, that are not zealous of his glorie. In the third of the Revelation, the fifteenth, thus writes the Spirit of God to the luke-warm Angell of the Church of the Laodiceans: <hi>I knowe thy workes</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:19133:14"/>(ſaith God), <hi>that thou art neither cold nor hot: I would thou wereſt cold or hot: therefore becauſe thou art luke-warm, and neither cold nor hot, it will come to paſſe, that I ſhall ſpue thee out of my mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O terrible voice of the juſt judgement of God! Wouldſt thou eſcape this judgement? wouldſt thou not be ſpewed out of the mouth of God? there is but one onely way ſet downe in the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. verſe of this chap. <hi>Be zealous therefore, and amend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be, vaine men (ſuch is their wretchednes) may caſt off the feare of theſe judgements for a while, by a continuall exchange in vanities; whil'ſt evill companie doth ſpare them no time to thinke of their end: But what will they doe, when that ſad day of their departure comes? when their ſoules perforce muſt bee taken from them? when they muſt leave all, and bid this world farewell for ever? what flatterer then can ſend them away with a quiet conſcience, and with ſolid comfort? what is he that can doe them anie good, or ſtand them in anie ſtead, when in all their life-time they have not purchaſed Chriſt for their friend?</p>
            <p>Remember therefore (O man), Remember whilſt thou haſt time, for what end thou art placed in this world: namely, that thou art here placed to be a probationer in the houſe of God, in a lower ſtraine to reſound his praiſes: where if thou ſhalt be found a proficient in grace and godlineſſe, then will the Lord advance thee unto that immortall Quire, unto the fellowſhip of Saints and Angels, there to ſing unto him more glorious HALE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LV-IAHS, for ever and for ever.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:19133:15"/>
            <p> Well then, this being thus; ſince the well fare and happineſſe of man depends upon the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable diſcharge of that duetie which he owes to God, both in himſelfe, and in thoſe that belong unto him: ſince it is of ſuch conſequence, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it procures mans eternall felicitie, being care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and rightly performed; or being neglected, his everlaſting miſerie: what wiſe man will not make it his chiefeſt ſtudie, to approove his waies unto the Lord? what wiſe man will not make it the verie joy of his heart, to doe the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſuch a God? what wiſe man will not binde himſelfe unto his duetie, and reſolve with <hi>Ioſhuah, I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am perſwaded, I need uſe no further induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to kindle your zeale; the verie mentioning of eternall life being enough to prevaile with the ſoule, which is created immortall. But perhapps you may put-in that queſtion here, which was made to <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, by thoſe new Converts in the ſecond of the <hi>Acts; What ſhall we doe?</hi> what rules canſt thou preſcribe us? what way canſt thou ſet us in this dutie? Give mee leave therefore, as farre as this ſcantling of time permits, to propoſe a few ſpeciall directions fit to be put in practice, if you have a deſire to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this dutie as it ought to be performed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whoſoever thou art that wouldeſt ſerve God ſoundly and ſincerely, thou and thy family (that ye may be the bleſſed of the Lord, thou and thy family) then with <hi>Davids</hi> bleſſed man, thy delight muſt be in the Law of the Lord, and in his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19133:15"/>Law thou muſt exerciſe thy ſelfe day and night. Here is true wiſedome to be learned: not ſuch as this world teacheth men, whereby to compaſſe their finiſter ends; but ſuch as will make thee wiſe in thy Calling; wiſe, to ſave thy ſelfe and them that heare thee; ſuch as will make thee perfect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everie good worke. Let others ſerve their luſts, and follow the vaine imaginations of their owne hearts: let them that luſt to periſh, adore the god of this world, and ſacrifice unto their owne nets; as for thee, whoſoever thou art, that aſpireſt unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie, let not this booke of the Law depart out of thy mouth, but meditate therein day and night, that thou mayeſt obſerve and doe according to all that is written therein: for then ſhalt thou make thy way proſperous, and then ſhalt thou have good ſucceſſe, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 1.8. A Chriſtians Library may ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt be furniſhed of all other Studies: it requires no moe bookes than two; the one, the booke of Gods Law, conteining the Theorie; the other, the booke of his owne Conſcience, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines the Practice of his duety. Oh what a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie ſtudent is he in the Schoole of grace, that keeps for himſelfe a true concordance out of theſe two!</p>
            <p>Why doe men buſie themſelves in needleſſe matters, and with a greedie curioſitie feed their fancies with impertinent trifles? What good doe our ſoules reape by the monſters of Affrica, or by the diſcoveries of America? Lo! here is that <hi>(u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num neceſſarium)</hi> vvhich includes the whole dutie of man, the Epitome of all profitable learning,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.42. <hi>Col.</hi> 12.13. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</note> which is only able to make us wiſe to ſalvation.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19133:16"/>
            <p> Theſe are thoſe bookes which thou ſhalt be put unto, upon the greateſt tryall that ever can befall thee, even upon life and death; not this temporall of the bodie, but that eternall of ſoule and bodie, before the Almightie Iudge of the world. In the twentith of the Revelation, and the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>I ſaw the dead</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>both great and ſmall, ſtand before God: and the bookes were opened, and another booke vvas opened, which is the booke of life; and the dead vvere iudged of thoſe things vvhich were written in the bookes, according to their vvorkes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well; the ſeeond rule that I will propoſe to be practiſed, for the right performance of this duetie to God, is this: If thou &amp; thy houſe wouldſt ſerve God, ſo as you ought to ſerve him, then know, that God hath ſet apart one day of the weeke for his ſervice: He allowes thee ſixe dayes, to ſpend upon thy ſelfe, but requires that thou ſhouldeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the ſeventh day unto him: and leſt thou mightſt forget it, he bids thee <hi>Remember</hi> to keep it holy. Oh denie him not ſo ſmall a requeſt, as one day, that hath given thee all. Nor hath he, for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, anie need of this from thee, but for thy ſake requires it of thee, with manifold bleſſings to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne it to thee. This day then thou muſt exempt from the vaine things of this world, and ſpend it wholly in pious duties, in religious exerciſes; in the Word, in the Sacraments; in the workes of mercie and charitie. Now thou muſt rouze up thy ſoule, and all that is within thee, to ſing prayſes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Name of the Lord, in the congregation of his Saints. Now thinke upon the glorious workes
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19133:16"/>of the Lord, the ſweet hope of thy redemption; the manifold benefites and conſolation that thou enjoyeſt in Chriſt: and then let thy raviſht ſoule burſt forth into thoſe glorious exultations of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid; It is a good thing to give thankes unto the Lord, and to ſing prayſes unto thy Name, O moſt High: to tell of thy loving kindneſſe in the morning, and of thy truth in the night ſeaſon, Pſal.</hi> 92.1.</p>
            <p>A third Rule I adde, and that is this: As the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath is appointed of God, to be wholly conſecrate unto his ſervice; ſo thou muſt let no day paſſe, without a ſpeciall remembrance of God. The Heathens, in their counterfeit Religion, yet retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this principle; <hi>A love princip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um</hi>—to begin the day, and whatſoever they undertooke, by firſt calling upon their gods: and ſhame it were for Chriſtians, to be more negligent in performing this ſervice unto the God of heaven, the true God, than Heathens were in performing it unto their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, which by nature were no gods. Therefore if thou wouldeſt be the true ſervant of God, thou muſt everie day call upon him, every day pray un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; privately by thy ſelfe, publikely with thy family: joyning together with one heart, and with one ſpirit, with reverence, with diligence, with fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vencie. This Rule wee may learne from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle: <hi>Pray alwayes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with all prayer and ſupplication in the Spirit;</hi> but how? <hi>and watching thereunto with all perſeverance, Epheſ.</hi> 6.18.</p>
            <p>The common ſort of Chriſtians doe ſhew by their careleſſe behavior, that they are fouly miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken what prayer is: they thinke it enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19133:17"/>the words; and ſo the tongue be buſie in ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, no matter what the heart is thinking: thus they turn the chiefeſt means of grace into the fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ſin that is, tempting the great majeſtie of God by their raſh preſumption. But if we would pray as we ought, we muſt come unto this dutie with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent preparation, behaving our ſelves as in the ſight of God. For this is an high &amp; heavenly duty, which makes us (as it were) familiar with God; whereby wee come into the preſence of God, and are vouchſafed, being but duſt and aſhes, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre with that glorious majeſtie of God: and therefore, unleſſe we meane to pull downe a curſe upon our ſelves, we muſt take heed how wee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ſo weightie and divine a dutie, careleſly, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally, and coldly.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake this with griefe of heart, and to our ſhame; no gariſh toy, no companie ſo vile and hatefull in the ſight of God, but is able to cauſe us to omit this duetie, and to break it off. What, my beloved? doe we thinke that God ſtands in ſuch need of our devotions, that when wee have ſerved the fleſh and the world, he will be contented with the refuſe of our time and affections? Oh no! we may learne farre better things of the Heathens; <hi>Ignavis precibus fortuna repugnat:</hi> Fortune (ſay they) reſiſteth cold and ſluggiſh prayers. And ſhall that ſervice bee thought meet by Chriſtians for the true and everliving God, which Heathens thought unmeet for their blind, their falſe, their imaginarie goddeſſe? Farre be this from us; wee have not ſo learned Chriſt</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:19133:17"/>
            <p> A fourth rule to be obſerved, that wee may bee the true ſervants of God, is, to withdraw our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections from worldly vanities: wee muſt take heed, that theſe get not the poſſeſſion of our hearts; if they doe, all that ſervice which wee ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme unto God, will ſoone vaniſh and come to nothing. <hi>Love not the world</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>neither the things that are in the world. If anie man love the world, the love of the Father is not him,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.15. For indeed, where the heart is taken up with vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, what roome can there be for pietie? There cannot bee two ſuch different maſters, as are the God of heaven, and the god of this world: And our Saviour plainely tells us, that no man can ſerve two maſters, without hating the one of them: <hi>Yee cannot</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>ſerve God and Mammon.</hi> Wee muſt therefore, according to that rule of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, ſo uſe the world, as if wee uſed it not; ſo uſe it, that we fall not in love with the vanities of it, that we be not enſnared with the deceitfulnes of it.</p>
            <p>A fift and laſt rule to be obſerved of us, if wee would ſhew our ſelves zealous in the ſervice of God, is firſt, that wee ſhould love and affect good men; cheriſh them and encourage them; keepe them with us, and converſe with them. A true friend (ſaith the proverbe) is a friend alſo to him that loves his friend. I may extend the nature of this proverbe to the true ſervants of God; they that ſerve God ſincerely themſelves, will make much of the ſervants of God. And <hi>David</hi> puts it for one of the characters and markes of him that ſhall reſt upon the holy hill of God, to make much
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19133:18"/>of them that feare the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.4. On the contrarie; thoſe that be ungodly and prophane, that deride all pietie and religion; ſuch as thoſe are, thy ſoule muſt hate and abhorre. <hi>David</hi> could tell no better way, whereby to make proofe of his zeale unto God, than by ſuch an affection. <hi>Doe not I hate them</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that hate thee?</hi> and <hi>doe not I riſe up againſt them that riſe up againſt thee? yea, I hate them right ſore as if they were mine enemies.</hi> If thou loveſt the Covenant of thy God, thou muſt deſpiſe them that deſpiſe that Covenant: If thou loveſt the law of thy God, thou muſt needs hate them that forſake that law: ſuch muſt not dwell with thee; ſuch muſt not tarrie in thy ſight. Doſt thou think that he can prove faithfull to thee, that prooves faithleſſe to God? or canſt thou endure that he ſhould be graced by thy countenance, that laies a reproch upon thy religion? Tis more than Chriſtian patience; ſuch was never in <hi>David;</hi> ſuch was never in <hi>Ioſhuah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee count him no loving ſubject, that harbors thoſe who deſpiſe &amp; reſiſt the lawes of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne. Shall we be ſo zealous for the honour of a mortall Prince, and ſhall wee be ſo careleſſe of the majeſtie of the immortall God?</p>
            <p>In the old law, he that deſpiſed <hi>Moſes</hi> law, died without mercy, under two or three witneſſes, <hi>Deu.</hi> 19.15. Marke now what the Apoſtle inferres up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this; <hi>Of how much ſorer puniſhment</hi> (ſaith hee,) <hi>ſuppoſe yee, ſhall he be worthie, which treadeth under foot the Sonne of God, and counteth the blood of the Teſtament as an unholy thing, wherewith he was ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19133:18"/>and doth deſpite the ſpirit of grace? Hebr,</hi> 10.29. You ſee it is no ſuch light matter to fall from the knowne truth, and to forſake the Goſpel of Chriſt, being ſo much more excellent than <hi>Moſes</hi> law was. Yet wee are dumbe and ſilent in Gods cauſe, and paſſe over theſe things as if they were done in another world, and did no whit concerne us; whilſt wee ſuffer that gangrene of hereſie to invade our families. Oh be not deceived: Everie maſter muſt give an account for everie ſervant hee keeps: And looke how manie ſuch deſpiſers of the word and truth of God are nouriſhed by him, ſo manie witneſſes will ſtand up againſt him in the day of the Lord, to convince him of coldneſſe and want of zeale.</p>
            <p>Here I have juſt occaſion to take up that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint &amp; reproofe which <hi>Eliah</hi> uſed towards the back-ſliding Iews of his time; <hi>How long halt ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two opinions? If the Lord be God, follow him; but if Baal be God, then follow him,</hi> 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 18.21. So ſay I, If this Goſpel w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> we preach unto you, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ye receive, be the Goſpel of Chriſt; if it be ſole &amp; ſufficient meanes unto ſalvation, why doe not yee receive it in uprightneſſe and ſincerity? why ſtand ye not up for Chriſt, and for the maintenance of his truth? why doe ye not labour to beate downe errours, and utterly ſuppreſſe the kingdome of Antichriſt? Take heed leſt your indifferencie herein, argue that yee belong not to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I will ſay no more, but onely cloſe up this point with that of <hi>Auſtin; Non amat Chriſtum, qui amat aliquid plus quam Chriſtum:</hi> He loves not Chriſt,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19133:19"/>that loves anie thing more than Chriſt: or with that which Chriſt himſelfe ſpeakes; He that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers any thing above Chriſt, is not worthy of him.</p>
            <p>I will now draw towards an end: yet before I conclude, one ſpeciall rubbe there is that I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move out of the way, principally of great men. What is that, ſay you? I will tell you: There is a generation of men, than which, never had the Church of God enemies more pernicious. Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in the third to the Philippians, hath ſet them forth in their lively character. The good Apoſtle, conſidering what miſchiefe they would doe in the Church of Chriſt, could not ſpeake of them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out manie a teare: <hi>Many</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>walke, of vvhom I have told you often, and now tell you even vveeping, that they are the enemies of the Croſſe of Chriſt; whoſe end is deſtruction, vvhoſe god is their belly, and whoſe glory is their ſhame; who mind earthly things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe walke from one houſe to another, and Chameleon-like, change their colour at everie change of ayre. Theſe are thoſe ungodly men, of whom S. <hi>Iude</hi> ſpeakes, that <hi>defile the fleſh, deſpiſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and ſpeake evill of dignities:</hi> by reaſon of whom, the way of truth is evill ſpoken of. Not the Miniſters of God, not the Word of God, no nor that drad and ſacred Majeſtie of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, can paſſe free from the poiſon of theſe mens lips. Theſe are they that buzze into your eares that curſed policie of wicked <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.31. to make Prieſts of the loweſt of the people. <q>Hold them ſhort (ſay they) and keepe them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, leſt they be too buſie with you.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:19133:19"/>
            <p> O full of all ſubtiltie and all miſchiefe, you chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Divell,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 15.10.</note> you enemies of all righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe! will you not ceaſe to pervert the right waies of the Lord? Behold now: whom doe you reſiſt? For, what are <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> but the miniſters, but the meſſengers of the Lord? I ſay it is the Lord himſelfe that you ſtrive againſt: your tongues are ſet againſt the moſt High; and hee will not faile to recompence your deſerts with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall flames.</p>
            <p>But as for you whom God advanceth in this world; if wee be ſo vile, ſo contemptible in your ſight, not to be thought worthie of acceſſe, nor to have that freedome of ſpeech which befits our place &amp; calling; we muſt ſuppe-up our contempt in ſilence, and thinke with <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.</note> 
               <hi>We had rather be doore-keepers in the houſe of our God.</hi> Nevertheleſſe we beſeech you, that you would ſometimes retire out of the vanity and deceitfulneſſe of this world, into your owne ſoules, &amp; conſider of your ſelves as you are men; not great and mightie, but fraile and mortal, which muſt die like one of the people, and give an account as well as the meaneſt of the multitude. There comes another world after this, where <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> ſhall both meete a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but upon othergeſſe tearmes than here in this world they did: for then the Martyr ſhall be ſet upon the Throne, whilſt the cruell King ſhall bee ſent unto the Priſon.</p>
            <p>What joy, what comfort or courage can the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God have, where the vileſt wretches may inſult over them? where they are debarred
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19133:20"/>that libertie which ever the Heathens had in their better times, <hi>Vbi vix ſentire que velis, nedum quae ſentias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tacit. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>hiſtor.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>dicere licet;</hi> Where they ſcarce dare think what they liſt, much leſſe ſpeake what they thinke.</p>
            <p>Certainly ſuch contempt of his meſſengers, God uſeth to pay home with his ſevereſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to furniſh them accordingly, where they be ſo ſlightly regarded. The Iewes did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe <hi>Ieremie,</hi> and that word which hee ſpake unto them in the name of the Lord: But what was the iſſue of this? Namely, that the Prophet ſhould not ſo much as pray for them, nor the name of the Lord be once mentioned amongſt that ungratefull people, <hi>Ier.</hi> 44. <hi>Ezechiel</hi> was reſtrained of his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, and deſpitefully handled, by the ſame ſtiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necked and rebellious nation: What doth God doe upon this? Hee makes the tongue of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet cleave to the roofe of his mouth; ſtrikes his meſſenger dumbe: and all to heape vengeance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, that he might ſet the dumbeneſſe of his prophet upon the ſcore of the peoples ſinnes, <hi>Eze.</hi> 3.25. <hi>Micah</hi> thinks it enough to keepe a Levite in his houſe to be his Prieſt, for ten ſhekells of ſilver and a ſuit of apparell by the yeare: he thinkes the Lord will be well-pleaſed with him for this: But what? was the Lord ever a whit the better pleaſed with him for this? No; <hi>Micah</hi> had a houſe of gods; and therefore the Lord ſends him a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Levite fit for a wicked Idolater, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 17.10.</p>
            <p>Well then, to returne and make an end of all; Whoſoever he is that would be the true ſervant of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19133:20"/>God, muſt thus thinke of himſelfe, that hee is a member of that holy and inviſible Church, w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> hath none in it but good men, none but gratious and godly men: therefore ſuch as theſe hee muſt embrace with a loving &amp; entire affection; to theſe he muſt joine &amp; unite himſelfe: yea, &amp; he muſt not contemne the faithfull meſſengers of the Lord, but have them in ſingular regard for their workes ſake. As for wicked men, that make but a mock of grace, theſe he muſt fly from as from ſerpents: they are onely ſet as ſnares in his way to keep him from the ſervice of God, and from the performance of religious dueties.</p>
            <p>Thus (right Honorable and Beloved) you have heard the ſumme and ſubſtance of thoſe points de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered and handled, which are included in this pithie and godly proteſtation of <hi>Ioſhuah.</hi> Firſt, from the connexion of my text, what conſtancie &amp; reſolution there is, &amp; ſhould be in thoſe that are the true ſervants of God. Though all the world revolt, yet they muſt cleave unto God. Secondly, from the high eſtate of him that proteſteth here, you have been taught from hence; that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of them for whom he hath done moſt in this world, that they ſhould bee moſt zealous for him. And laſtly, from the extent of it, you have heard, that the true ſervants of God will keepe none in their houſes, but ſuch as joine with them in the true worſhiping of God. You have heard theſe points handled and proſecuted at large; I muſt not dwell upon particulars. Onely give mee leave to end
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19133:21"/>with a word or two of exhortation.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> in the beginning of his ſpeach, ſought to ſtirre up the Iſraelites unto the feare and obedience of the Lord, by rehearſing what God had done for them: So may I, with as good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, lay the ſame ground of exhortation in the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up of mine. Now then, by the tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of our God, by all the benefits which we have received of him, which are infinite in number, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable in value: by our great and manifold de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances, not (as the Iſraelites) from the downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right violence of Perizzites &amp; Iebuſites, but from the furious and treacherous conſpiracies of more ſubtile, more cruell, more politicke, more malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, more inhumane enemies: By the ſweet peace and quiet proſperitie of our countrie: By this bleſſed and free paſſage of the Goſpell of peace, which doth everie where diſplay its pure and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial beames; being hid in none, but in them that periſh: By thoſe better things which God hath prepared for his ſervants in the life to come, even the joyes of heaven, ſuch as no eye hath ſeene, no tongue can relate, nor ever have entered into the heart of man.</p>
            <p>O let this ſtirre up in us a readineſſe, a reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a zeale to this dutie: To feare God; to love God with all our heart, with all our ſtrength, with all our might: To referre our actions wholly unto the glorie of our God: To ſerve him in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the dayes of our life.</p>
            <p>But if ſuch unſpeakeable bountie, ſuch heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19133:21"/>goodneſſe, cannot winne our earthly and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſoules: yet know this, there is a Hell, and there be damned; and torments in verie deed, ſuch as no patience is able to beare, no date of time weare out. If yee care not for his mercies, yet feare his judgements. Nevertheleſſe, why will wee tempt and provoke his juſtice, who is ſo rich in mercie? O rather, ſince there is mercie with God, therefore let him be feared. This it is which ſhould make us cheerful in the ſervice of our God, which ſhould make us performe willing obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to our Lord; Knowing, that if we ſerve him here, wee ſhall raigne with him hereafter: if wee ſet our delight upon him here, wee ſhall be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his preſence hereafter; if wee give glory unto him whilſt we live here, hereafter wee ſhall triumph with him, and be received into glorie.</p>
            <p>Now the God of heaven, &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>Soli Deo ſapienti gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
